Was hast Du am 7. Oktober erlebt?
Wow...
6:30 in the morning I woke up to the sound of alarms,
which we are used to, unfortunately.
We ran to the safe room,
where my children sleep,
me and my husband and the dogs,
and we closed the door and we waited for it to finish.
But it didn’t finish,
it was unstoppable and it was very close.
It was right in the neighborhoods where people live,
and...
I think that it was 20 minutes after that,
that we turned the television on...
And we saw the white pickup trucks in Sderot
with the...
the terrorists on them,
and that moment I looked at it and I said
"Oh my god"
"If this is happening in Sderot",
which is about 15 minutes drive from here,
"What on earth is happening in my kibbutz?",
and...
there was...
at that time there were already
terrorists inside the kibbutz,
but we didn’t know it.
I live in the center of the kibbutz,
and they entered through the back gate,
to another neighborhood that was quite far from mine,
and they started breaking in.
One of the first places they came was here,
to the dairy farm.
There were two people working there that morning.
Two students...
lovely students from Tanzania.
Every year Tanzania sends
top students here,
in order to learn agriculture,
and bring it back to their country.
Really amazing young people,
Every time I speak about it I can’t...
They came inside here,
there were two students. One of them managed to
run away, the other one was caught by Hamas.
He was tortured and murdered
and they took his body to the Gaza Strip.
We first thought that he was only kidnapped,
but then we realized that,
they killed him.
The father came all the way from Tanzania
to take his son's body
and they wouldn’t release the body,
The body is still there for 2 years,
his name was Joshua Luito Malal.
Sweet, sweet boy.
Then they ran
to that direction over there.
That's the neighborhood where
the Thai people that work here in the kibbutz sleep.
And they started running,
into their...
The Thai
started running away. I'm sorry for the description,
but one of them was caught and was killed,
was murdered with a shovel.
And the rest of them,
there were a few more that were injured,
the rest of them started running,
carrying the injured, also,
started running towards the neighborhood,
that was next to them.
There was one house in that neighborhood they rent to,
that was two stories high,
and there was a father there, his son,
for Shabbat,
He came from the army.
He's in the army and he came,
so he had a M16 in his
House and he told his wife,
he put his family in one of the safe rooms,
and he told his wive:
"Nobody will get near this neighborhood",
"I will make sure that...", they had like a little
mini neighborhood of five houses.
He stands there and he sees the
Thai people running towards the neighborhood,
He runs down,
he opens the door, he lets them all in,
and he puts them with his family.
And he goes back upstairs and started shooting
the terrorists.
My sister was his neighbor,
her house was just in front of his.
And my parents were also there that day,
and it was a holiday,
they came to visit and the lock of
her safe room, the window was...
was broken...
My sister's safe room,
the lock of the window was broken,
and one of the terrorists spots it from outside.
And they start running towards my sister's window
and there started a battle.
On one side it was my brother in law, holding
the shutters, and on the other side,
there were the terrorists trying to open it.
I was with them on the phone at the same time,
and I could hear the screaming of my nephews,
and...
I can hear that there's,
and then I hear shooting. Their neighbor Ran Poslushni,
the sweet, sweet Ran that we always remember as a true hero,
he shot them and saved my family.
At a certain point,
that day
Ran was shot and killed and
This brave man managed to save
approximately 40 people before he before he died.
Before he was murdered.
A very sad story.
Because I was head of education,
there were a few teenagers
that felt comfortable speaking to me.
And the teenagers that day went through really
difficult
situations because
You’re not a child anymore,
you’re not a grown up anymore,
but people trust you to do things so...
some of them really
had to take care of entire families.
I'm going to read you a very small part
of a very long texting
between me and a fourteen-and-half year old
brave, brave, brave girl.
This girl started texting me
around 7:45 in the morning and
this texting finished around 11 at night,
it’s so long.
I'm not going to read it all of course,
because it kinds of repeats itself also.
She started texting me at
A 7:45 in the morning,
and...
I was in a different neighborhood,
so we were experiencing a whole different scenario.
I'm going to read it from the middle.
This is 9:45 in the morning.
This girl is with her mother and her younger brother
in their house. The mother is paralyzed with fear.
The older brother,
who's about 18
is in another neighborhood of the kibbutz,
he has his own unit.
And, she starts crying for help.
Straight in the morning this is 9:45.
"I hear them right outside my house",
"they are shouting, they are shooting"
"Please someone come help"
"they are shouting and shooting outside my house"
"we must keep quiet they are shouting again",
"I'm scared as Oshrit. I'm almost out of battery"
I start
trying to calm her down and I tell her to
close all the apps in the background to save battery.
"Oh my God they are shouting right here"
"Oh my God, Oshrit, they are right here outside my house",
"I can really hear them"...
I tell her, 09:50 am,
I tell her "breathe, honey".
"The army is patrolling, I am sure that the IDF is here"
Because who would have thought...
"Please send someone"
"Please send someone, they are shooting",
"Please send someone now".
Now look at the how resourceful she was.
The phone of her mother was out of battery,
and in many of the neighborhoods,
there was no electricity nor communication.
Many of the...
How do you say that?
Many of the infrastructures
were damaged that day.
So, her mom didn’t have a phone,
and as I told you before,
Us, the adults, we get the security messages to our phones.
so she asks me to send every message to her phone,
so she will know what was going what's going on.
09:57 am
"Oshrit, he's right here he's shooting outside the house quickly, quickly",
I say "maybe it’s the army shooting?",
"I hear shouting in Arabic".
"Please bring someone, my mum is stressed",
"she wants to know what's going on"
"What about my brother? I'm so worried".
At a certain point,
her brother starts sending her messages,
telling her that he's in another room at the kibbutz,
with another friend and that they are in the safe room,
there's a battle on the handle of the safe room.
Because there are terrorists on the other side of the door,
trying to break in.
He starts writing,
look who is,
who is texting for help,
his fourteen-and-half year old sister,
and he starts telling her
that he can’t hold it anymore,
that if they will not send somebody,
he's going to die,
and at a certain point he gets completely crazy,
just from the whole situation,
and he starts writing her messages saying
"Stop lying to me",
"you’re always saying you'll send somebody",
"Nobody is coming", and really he completely lost it.
And this amazing brave girl,
she sends all the messages to me,
and she keeps instructing me,
where the houses are,
where they are at.
I don’t know what to do.
I'm trapped in my safe room,
and I have no idea what's happening around the kibbutz,
I have no idea who's alive,
who's dead...
I already realized at 10:00 in the morning,
that this is a deadly scenario going on.
I start writing texts. I think,
Every person
that might have anything to do with security
on the kibbutz.
And I start sending the messages like crazy.
End of the day we realized that I was sending messages
sometimes to people that were already dead,
but with this texting,
this girl,
saved her entire family.
The whole day she sent forces to her family's house,
and to her brother's unit.
10:30: "I'm stressed",
"they are shooting all of the over the place"
"They're in the house, the whole house is falling apart"
"Send someone quickly Oshrit, quickly".
"They're breaking in, they're inside the house",
"my mom is about to faint"
At this point, I send her a prayer from psalms for protection...
Because that's all I can do.
And I write "pray"
"pray"...
She's saying "my mom is not breathing anymore"
"They are breaking things, they are breaking in"
"We must keep quiet, we must keep quiet",
"there are screamings, please help us",
"Please help us"
This goes on and on and on and on...
We realized only later on
that there were so many cries for help,
from so many different people,
that it was very difficult for the amount of
üeople that were fighting the battle,
to get to everyone.
We had 14 people on the kibbutz,
that were fighting the battle,
Against 350 terrorists that came in,
in a community that has less than 500 people,
including children.
our luck firstly was that
They came in three different waves and not all at once,
that the 14 people that were at the kibbutz,
even though 11 of them were very trained soldiers,
of course they couldn’t defeat them.
The gap in the numbers is unbelievable,
but what they could do was slow them down,
and harass them. And every time someone called for help,
they just used to go there and drive them away,
scare them away.
They managed to kill many of them,
but they didn’t,
they of course couldn’t,
defeat them.
So what they did was that they held this place until
more reinforcement came around
01:15 afternoon,
01:15 pm, they came,
there came more forces inside the kibbutz,
and they helped
the people from here to fight the battle.
The second wave of terrorists
came through the front gates of the kibbutz,
which is closer to where I live,
and they split to two.
One went straight towards my house,
and the other one went
right.
There was a row of houses,
the first row of houses right next to the front gate,
and they started the massacre journey
throughout those houses.
At that time I'm sitting with my children and my family,
and I see my husband, he sat
with a laptop and he turns it on,
and I see him turn completely pale,
and he signals me quietly,
so the children will not be bothered,
and what we see is unbelievable.
Hamas had the GoPro cameras,
so not only they filmed the entire thing,
they live streamed it. And not only that,
they live streamed it on the same families'
social media.
The families that they were just capturing, torturing,
murdering whatever.
They put it on their social media,
so their friends and families could see it real time,
What is happening to them.
Which is really,
really,
A sick idea.
I was a few houses from there and I see
my neighbors and friends,
the first video we see is of the Elyakim-Arava family,
I'm not sure which one I saw first but...
And we see that
the family sits down looks terrorized,
they were all around them terrorists,
they had three children there.
One 8 years old one 15 years old and one 17.
Two girls,
and the 17 year old guy.
And what Hamas did was take the 17 year old,
Tomer Arava Eliaz,
A brave, brave young man,
they put a gun to his head,
and they told him to go around houses,
knocking on doors, telling people to get out.
Now he was a very brave young man,
and we know for a fact that
by the ability of knowing
the surroundings,
he managed to save a few families.
He was just honored by the president of Israel,
his memory was honored.
At a certain point,
he ran away from Hamas, he tried running away,
his body was found not far from the front gate,
we don’t know how exactly he died, but he died.
The other members of the family,
the father's body was found in the outskirts of Gaza.
The mother and the two girls she was holding,
according to the girl's testimony,
she was holding them in both hands,
telling them not to be worried or afraid,
because they're together and she's going to protect them,
and...
that second she gets shot in the head.
And, the two girls one 8 years old and one 15,
are taken to Gaza as hostages,
after seeing their entire family...
die...
And they are staying there,
for two months,
until the second hostage deal.
They didn’t come back in a good shape,
to say the least.
The second
Video that we see is of the Idan family.
We see again the family sitting on the floor.
Again, we see the father wounded,
we think that he is wounded,
but we realized later on
that it was the blood of his daughter.
Of his 18 year old daughter
that was murdered right next to him,
when she tried helping him protect,
guard the door of the safe room.
We can hear the brother asking,
"but why did you kill her?"
"She was just a child",
and we didn’t know which of his sisters
he was referring to.
It’s a certain point,
when Tomer Arava walked
with the terrorists, he reached
another neighborhood
and he knocked on the doors over there,
and he said to many of the people
"Don’t come out".
And then,
one of the houses that he knocked on,
there was Omri and Lishay Miran,
and they are such good spirits,
good souls, that they couldn’t hear a 17 year old,
in that situation. They were with a baby and a toddler,
and they decided to put their knives down,
and open the door.
They were taken,
and put with the Idan family in the same house,
and suddenly we see on the video,
we see the Idan family also,
Wow...
And...
What happens there is that...
There wasn't a pattern of who they take,
and what they do.
Every scenario was different.
So in this case they decided to take only the two men.
Omri Miran and Tsachi Idan, the two fathers.
They took them to Gaza Strip.
We know today that Tsachi was dead since December 2023, probably.
But since then,
we got so many different
contradicting messages from Hamas,
so just think about how horrible it is for a family.
"He's alive",
"Now he's dead",  "now he's ...",
it really a vicious
warfare.
Omri Miran, our dear friend,
is still held captive in Gaza for over 700 days,
almost two years,
and we hope that he's
as healthy as possible
and we are waiting and praying to get him back.
To get him back.
And to get the body of Joshua Loitu Mollel
back to his family in Tanzania.
Ah, we pray for it.
Anyway...
I was in my house and
my son is handicapped,
back then he used to walk with a walker,
And, the bombardment was so heavy that day, that we all,
were staying in the safe room,
and there was not enough room for the walker,
and besides we thought that...
There were many people,
because we stayed so long
in the safe rooms,
there were many people who used a bucket or a bottle,
if they needed to relieve themselves.
My son couldn’t,
he had to have his accessible toilet.
So, we had to
go out of the safe room a few times that day.
We started thinking about
what would be the safest way to do it,
so we thought that if he goes with the walker,
he will not have enough time to turn around,
if he needs to
come back to shelter.
So we decided we’re going to throw
the walker away for the day and every time he needed
to go,
we just grabbed him, each parent by one shoulder, and
carried him to the toilet. "Operation Toilet",
it was every time now.
Every time like this took a few attempts,
because the bombardment was so heavy.
And there was even one time,
that we already sat him down,
and we had to grab him and run back.
One of those
"Toilet adventures", as I come back from them,
I believe it was about a 01:45 pm.
I go back with my husband and my son to the safe room.
I'm about to enter the safe room,
and I hear someone playing with my door handle,
and in the window next to the door,
I see the barrel of an M16,
and of course the first thing
I think of is to run away
and close the door of the safe room and lock it.
So there were,
there was a person there,
and he could see me in an angle,
but he could see me if he went
he couldn’t shoot me because the angle was too sharp,
through the window like that, through the glass,
and he sees me and he starts shouting:
"IDF, IDF open up!"
So I look at him and I do see that he has IDF uniform,
but you can put on whatever shirt you want,
and it’s my children over here,
and I don’t know what to do,
and I turn around again to go to the safe room.
I'm right next to the door of the safe room,
and then he starts shouting at me:
"No please",
"Please don’t go, we’re Jewish",
"we swear we’re Jewish"
and then I hear that there's a bunch of men outside
my door and they start shouting Jewish symbols,
so I know that they are from ours.
They said "today is Simchat Torah",
"we were supposed to do Hakafot in the evening",
"we’re just in the middle of Hagei Tishrei",
"we just finished Yom Kippur"
And I try to think as fast as I can,
should I trust it, should I not,
what should I do?
And then I get this idea,
and apparently I wasn't the only one,
there were plenty of people who thought of that,
I asked them to pray. I say,
"If you’re Jewish I want to hear a Jewish prayer"
Because I thought it would be something
that is very difficult to mimic,
a prayer.
And they started praying.
And I open the door and until today,
my husband laughs at me that
my husband at my wedding did not get such a hug,
I fell on this guy's neck
and the first thing that we thought was "Yay".
"The IDF is here it’s over"
But we were so far from the truth.
It wasn't the IDF as an army.
The IDF as an army lost that day.
It’s very difficult to comprehend it,
trust me,
for Israelis it’s even way harder to comprehend it,
but the IDF lost the battle that day.
The people who came were actually private people
from around the country,
who saw the news,
and call their friends and came in
and put on their uniform and their weapons,
in huge groups.
They were friends from the army,
and they just came down in huge groups,
to help.
From that moment on,
we stayed 12 more hours in the safe room with horrible,
horrible battles going on all around us.
The things that this girl,
that fourten-and-half-year-old was telling me by WhatsApp,
in the morning arrived to my neighborhood,
and I can feel,
it already started at 10:30 when the first,
when the second wave of terrorist came
into my neighborhood.
There were plenty of stories in my neighborhood,
there was
an 80 year old man that said to his family
to go to the safe room while he sat in the living room,
Right in front of the big window to be seen first.
His thought was, his plan was, that they will see him,
shoot him and continue, and his family will be saved.
And that's exactly what happened,
they shot him dead,
he was sitting in the living room,
just in front of the window,
acting as if he was reading the newspaper
he was shot dead but they continued going,
and they didn’t go after his family.
Really...
We hear, I can’t even...
All you hear all day long are the explosions,
and if there's something that I really,
really hope that you will never hear in your life,
is a rocket falling just 2 meters,
3 meters from you.
This is something that shakes your entire soul and body,
and this was the noise that
I couldn’t get out of my head for like
a year and a half.
Wow it was so...
They launch the rockets right on the houses.
The house behind mine
was the first one to get hit by a rocket that day,
and we were very worried about the family,
that was there for the entire time,
because they also didn’t have infrastructures,
and they couldn’t communicate.
I ended up calling the mother
of the husband.
She was abroad.
Poor, poor woman.
And I didn’t know that she's also from our kibbutz,
and I didn’t want to panic her,
I said like
"No, everything is under control",
I didn’t tell her that I was worried about them.
End of the day they were okay,
we sent the army over there to check.
The other noise that was very,
very significant that day was of the weapons
Like...
You hear it,
we heard it 20 hours non stop,
and that was
a sound that was very difficult for me
to get out of my head.
After we were evacuated from the kibbutz,
I think it was a month after,
I was sitting with friends outside in the evening,
and suddenly I hear that noise, that...
And I just get up and I duck,
And I look around me,
and I see a woman walking with a stroller on pebbles,
and I hear a battlefield.
So that was really made me understand
that it’s going to take a while,
until that trauma...
We were like zombies for quite a long time.
One thing I remember very vividly
is that
when they said that they are going to evacuate us,
it was around 9:00 pm,
and we got a message
saying that we are going to get evacuated,
but they said do not get out of the safe rooms.
Only when soldiers come to your house,
and then you will have 2,
3 minutes to gather things that you need,
and you will go out.
And, it was already 2:00 am,
It was already 2:00 am and they still haven’t reached
my neighborhood. Almost 2:00.
and...
the WhatsApp groups of the women
were very active that day.
So my neighbors and I,
we had the "2:00 am pact", we call it,
we said,
we spoke on the phone, we said, okay,
the people that are evacuating us,
they don’t know the kibbutz,
they don’t know who's in every house,
and we need to make sure that nobody is forgotten.
So we had a list of all the names of
my closest
neighbors.
We said, if they get here,
we vowed that if the army gets here,
we make sure that they take everyone.
I had a list: Katia, Ravid,
Adi, Yochi...
I had a list,
I had to make sure that they are being evacuated
when I was evacuated, and we all had that agreement.
One thing that you have to understand is that
we didn’t have a clue about what was going on.
I didn’t know about the Nova (Festival),
I didn’t know about, I had no idea,
I was in my safe room,
and apart from getting text messages,
I didn’t know.
They took us to...
They found this place in the kibbutz,
in one of the places in the outskirts of the kibbutz.
Far from the...
Far, farther away from Gaza,
and they brought...
They always brought about 50 people to that place,
they brought a bus and
sent them away from the kibbutz.
So because it took it took so long,
they started from
the neighborhoods that were attacked
a lot harsher than mine,
it took us time.
So they put us on a bus,
they took us to a place called Mishmar HaNegev,
which is about 40 minutes drive.
The kibbutz was filled with bodies,
and I thanked god for not taking me at 9:00 pm,
but taking me at 2:00 am, so my children couldn’t see,
it was so dark outside, so it was spared from them,
that ended up to be a blessing.
Horrible, horrible views.
On the roads...
Horrible views.
I speak with a friend from Mefalsim,
She gets out of her kibbutz to evacuate because
they weren't evacuated because
they were not the closest to the border,
and they managed
to defeat,
they had much less,
less terrorists came and they were able to defeat them.
So people said "okay,"
"Mefalsim,"
"They got it going everything is fine".
And then she drives out of her kibbutz and she's saying,
she's saying to me:
"Everybody is... It’s like a graveyard",
And, she gets crazy she's going like
"Everybody's dead, everybody's dead",
She starts screaming,
she calls her husband,
and he just
guides her on,
he says "Step on the gas",
"Step on the gas, keep on going".
"Keep on going, you can do this",
And she,
her alone with her children,
It was a horror.
It was a scene from a horror...
Not even a movie,
it’s completely reality,
and they...
We were evacuated to Mishmar HaNegev,
and I will always,
in my life, remember, that in Mishmar HaNegev,
they put some
tea and coffee and some cakes for us,
and in order to get to the hall,
where everybody was gathering,
I needed to take few steps and step down,
go down to the place,
I call it "The stairs of death".
Every step I took I heard of another friend
that I will never see again.
It was the start of a body count
that we had to
to face and
It was a very long one because
firstly,
there were people that we didn’t know
whether they were kidnapped,
or murdered brutally and we cannot identify the body,
there were people from other kibbutzim that...
There was this thing.
Between everyone.
We were scared of sending messages to friends
from other kibbutzim. It took us
3, 4 days.
We were looking for lists,
And, when we finally did send messages,
it was more or less the same all around the region.
It was "just give us a sign of life"
Oh...
Every message like that,
that I got from a friend, was like
"Oh my God"...
"She's alive" or "he's alive".
"Oh my God thank God"
And every answer that I got,
there were people,
I didn’t have the guts to send a message to.
I just waited for them to contact me.
So, every day and for a long time,
you hear, you’re going from a funeral to a memorial to a...
To give your condolences,
it’s just, we just couldn’t.
The amounts were horrific.
And, then it took us a very long time,
to get back on our feet,
I can’t even say that we’re back on our feet yet,
I can say that very good people from Israel,
and from around the world,
really many,
especially Jews,
but not only, not only. Many people, Christians.
Oh my God...
We got so much help
from Christians around the world.
We were just
embraced with a very warm embrace.
You asked me earlier about
the Israeli Muslims or Israeli Arabs.
What happened then was that
many of them came also to where we were evacuated to,
And they came also to bring help.
And when I said to one of them,
there was one of them that came with a car,
with a pickup truck,
really filled with aid for us,
and I remember that I said "Thank you",
and he started crying,
and he said to me "Don’t thank me",
"It happened to all of us".
"What happened to you, it happened to all of us"
He said "Every peaceful person of the Middle East,".
"every moderate person of the Middle East,"
"It was an attack of all on all of us",
"so don’t you say thank you."